Hi, welcome back to the lamrim. We're on episode 13.
I call it, It Might Set the Sky Afire.
It Might Set the Sky Afire.
Just to get us into the mood of this episode
I'd like to show a picture. This is a,
this is actually the first detonation of a nuclear weapon
in this world. This was in,
near the end of World War two and
actually this bomb was exploded not far from here.
I have driven there before. It's a few hours drive from where I'm speaking,
in New Mexico in the United States.
These scientists, including Fermi and earlier Einstein and
Oppenheimer, who worked at Princeton,
they believed it was theoretically possible to create a nuclear
reaction
and it would create a large bomb and
they talked the president United States into this project
to make this bomb.
When they had it ready in theory, they took it to New Mexico,
near here, and they
set it off in the morning one day out in a desert.
The project was called Trinity. It's just sort of meaning like a powerful deity.
I read some amazing conversations
with the scientists and the military people.
The military people said, "Is this safe, you know, if we explode this bomb could
something happen that we don't know about?" And the scientists were like, "No, no, you know, we'll make enough
explosion to destroy a city for example,
so don't don't worry about it,
we've got it understand under control."
And then,
this one scientist raised his hand and I just,
somebody should make a movie about it.
He raised his hand and
he said, "There's a small chance of a problem.'" The military guys are like, "What?" And he said, "Well,
we don't quite know,
but there's a, there is some chance that it will ignite the whole atmosphere of earth and it will destroy
everything on earth and all the people on earth. There's a chance that the reaction will go through the oxygen of the entire earth."
You know. And they're like, "Okay, just a chance, right?" "Yeah, just a chance."
"Let's go ahead with it."  I'm sorry, whenever I read that I was like wow.
They're trying to do a little bomb and
it could go wrong, you see. It could
destroy everything.
And that's the theme of this episode 13. All right. Let's read the Tibetan together.
GZHAN YANG SNGAR BSHAD PA'I BRAM ZE'I KHYE'U TZA NA KYA'I BYUNG BA DANG,
So now they're talking about
disastrous results of
diamond way practice if we don't have this attitude of trying to help,
having made a commitment to help everyone, okay?
Then this is a story, this says, "It's like the story of the Bhraman
youth
called Chanakya." which we talked about earlier, so I went back and got it for you.
And,
the text earlier in the lamrim,
day 13,
it says, [see folio 225b, Gift 26, meditation2, 4th paragraph] BRAM ZE'I KHYE'U TZA NA KYA ZHES PA
GSHIN RJE GSHED GRUB PAS MI MANG PO MNGON SPYOD KYI MTHUS BSAD PAS DMYAL BA MNAR MED DU SKYES PAR GSUNGS
"He got magical powers by practicing tantra and then he misused them
and he actually
killed
a number of people with the powers that he gained through the practice of the secret teachings."
So here it says,"Then he went to the lowest of the hell realms." So we're talking about,
before we had the example of someone who
didn't use the power of tantra
correctly and all that happened was they saw emptiness directly.
And now we're talking about other people who didn't have this bodhichitta
motivation
and when they practice tantra, it got worse.
It was like the whole sky blew up. It's like they ended up in the hell realms
because they were doing these powerful practices
without this motivation to help all living beings.
Alright, there are three stories.
RGYA GAR NA GSHIN RJE GSHED SGRUB PA'I RNAL 'BYOR BA ZHIG GDUG 'DRER SKYES TE BOD DU 'ONGS PAR
JO BOS GTOR MA BYIN NAS PHAR BSKRAD PA DANG,
Then there's a story of a
yogi, a tantrica in India
who was practicing Yamari.
In Tibetan it's called GSHIN RJE GSHED. It's similar to Yamantaka.
He was reborn as a
spirit, as a negative spirit, a bad spirit.
These spirits tend to wander into other places,
so he actually wandered up towards Tibet and he reached Tibet.
Atisha became aware of the spirit and
kind of like a, made a deal with him, where he offered him a torma and
and then chased him off. So  PHAR BSKRAD PA
GTOR MA BYIN NAS PHAR BSKRAD PA
means Lord Aisha gave him a
a torma offering and then he chased him off. He said, "Now you should go."
So this is again a
disaster result
from practicing the higher teachings without this mo, without this commitment to these beings.
Third story here:
'PHAN PO'I 'JIGS BYED KYI RNAL 'BYOR PA ZHIG
YI DVAGS YI DAM GYI GZUGS CAN ZHIG TU SKYES TE
SNGAR GYI NYE GNAS LA
GSUR BSGUGS PA'I LO RGYUS LTAR YIN,
This again is a story that was told before.
'PHAN PO'I is an area
of Tibet,
I think it's north of Lhasa. I'm not sure. I've known some monks from there.
'JIGS BYED KYI RNAL 'BYOR PA ZHIG
There was a
tantrica practicing Yamantaka and
he was born
YI DAM GYI GZUGS CAN ZHIG
This is a weird word. Okay, I should offer Seiji a $100. You ready?
Or Tim, YI DVAGS,
YI DAM GYI GZUGS CAN.
YI DAM GYI GZUGS CAN. Okay. YI DVAGS you know.
A PRETA, right?
What's a YI DAM? Yea, tantric deity.
GZUGS CAN?
GZUGS?
GZUGS.
skye
He was born. Okay, cancel the bet. He was born into the form of what?
No.
YI DVAGS.
He was born as a PRETA, but he looked like
Yamari. A very weird karma okay, he practiced tantra
without a high motivation,
he was constantly thinking about this fierce deity,
and he died and he was reborn as a PRETA,
but the PRETA looked like the fierce deity.
That's all he got, that was his result of his tantric practice.
GZUGS CAN ZHIG
Then some of his friends who had done
the Yamari retreat with him
were offering a torma
to the local spirits and he showed up.
Yeah, and they were like, "Hey are you Yamrari?"
He says, "Uh, uh, I'm your old friend, you know, and I tried to practice tantra
without this motivation.
So all I got was I look like him, but I live like a PRETA.
I'm suffering terribly."
It'd be weird to meet your retreat friends later
and they look at you and they say, "Oh Yamari's here." And you say, "No. I'm not Yamari,
I'm just a plain old PRETA thing, you know,
please give me someTORMA
Please leave me TORMAS more frequently."
You don't want to go to Diamond Mountain on a retreat, practice Meda Buddha, practice Medicine Buddha, get the Medicine Buddha
initiation online, okay, and
do the retreat online at home and then you die and
you become a ghost
that looks like Medicine Buddha, I'd be weird, right? And then your friends are offering TORMAS and you show up.
It's a weird story. Okay, we don't want to do that.
DA LTA'ANG PHAL CHER GYIS YI DAM GYI ZHAL GZIGS
DANG MNGON SHES RDZU 'PHRUL SOGS
LA RTZIGS CHE BAR BYED
Then nowadays,
If, PHAL CHER means most people,
if they see a
tantric deity in person
YI DAM GYI ZHAL GZIGS, ZHAL GZIGS
means if they see the face of the
tantric deity that they're praying to
or
they gain some kind of ability to
read other people's minds or they
can fly in the sky or they know people
who say I met Tara in person, or
I can read, I can read what you're thinking or
I can fly in the sky.
And then people are like,
"Wow, your practice is awesome.
You must have a really good
buddhist practice if you can see deities and
you can read people's minds and you can fly in the sky." And then Pabongka Rinpoche says
"Yeah, that's cool, but if you don't have bodhichitta, you could go to hell because of those three.
They could take you to hell."
Seeing deities
flying in the sky,
reading other people's minds.
If you do it for the wrong reason
It could take you to the hell realms,
if you don't have bodhichitta.
DES NA MNGON SHES RDZU 'PHRUL GANG DANG LDAN YANG PHAN MI THOGS,
So it doesn't really help you and me if we can read other people's minds or
we can do little magic tricks.
PHAN MI THOGS,  means it doesn't help us that much.
SEMS 'DI YOD NA
NI GZHAN CI LA'ANG MA BRTZON KYANG,
But, if you get this experience where you meet
other beings directly and make a commitment
to them for their happiness,
THEG PA CHEN PO'I CHOS KYI RTZA BA BYUNG BA YIN TE
then you really reached the essence of Dharma.
You have the essence of Dharma inside of you. Forget
meeting tantric deities, forget
having the ability to read other people's minds.
If you just have this kind of love
from a personal bond with each being and
a commitment to them, to help them, to take care of them, as if you were their parent,
then that's really the core of the Dharma.
MDO SNGAGS GANG GI SKABS KYANG
THEG CHEN DU 'GYUR MI 'GYUR SEMS 'DI YOD MED KYI RJES SU 'GRO,
Whether or not
we can call you someone who's practicing the bodhisattva way,
only depends on this experience.
It's the crux of the whole question,
is have you met beings,
have you made this commitment to them
or at least are you aspiring to that?
Then we can say you're on the bodhisattva track or not.
These, by the way, you can have the, it can be that you haven't had that
experience directly, but you're strongly attracted to it, that's fine.
'DIS ZIN NA, DUD 'GRO LA ZAN CHANGS GCIG BYIN PA TSUN DANG,
So the next picture here
is a pic, is a cute picture. Where's that, of a bird?
This is a lady and she's feeding a bird. And this is a practice that I used to do with my former partner
Christi, and it was a very sweet practice.
We used to go to McDonald's, the only thing we could eat at McDonald's was French fries.
We had read this part of the lamrim and
we would take
little pieces of French fries. So, you know the story of the tigress, when Lord Buddha in his former life
was a prince called, I think his name was Nyingtob Chenpo, Big,
Big courage, Mr. Courage. And he went into the jungle and he found a
tigress
who was dying of hunger and had four babies who were trying to nurse from her but couldn't.
She couldn't produce milk.
To make a long story short, he offers her
his body.
He offers the five his body
if they make, you know with a commitment that they should be his first five students and they were.
Kualdinya and four others.
There's this act of truth you can do by feeding another being.
So we used to go to McDonald's order of French fries,
break them up into little pieces and then we would feed the bird, the sparrows
who come to the McDonald's.
We would make a prayer, if you eat my French fry,
then you're going to be reborn as my student when I become a Buddha.  So then it becomes very cool to go McDonald's.
Otherwise, it's kind of weird to go to McDonald's, right?
So actually he mentions it here
, DUD 'GRO LA ZAN CHANGS GCIG BYIN PA TSUN DANG,
If you have
this kind of motivation and you go to a McDonald's and you feed
pieces of French fries to the little birds there,
KUN SPYOD LUNG MA BSTAN RNAMS KYANG RDZOGS BYANG THOB PA'I RGYUR 'GYUR
Even
activities which are karmically flat,
okay, they have no great karmic
power. Giving French fries to a bird or going to the toilet in the McDonald's.
Karmically neutral activities. It's called here, LUNG MA BSTAN.
Karmically neutral activities.
I mean giving the French fries to the birds is a little bit good karma.
Let's say you go in and you want to use the toilet so you buy some French fries. Sometimes I do that.
Even the going to the toilet, which by definition is almost karmically neutral, not good, not bad.
I guess it depends on how bad a bomb you make.
But uh,
it's karmically neutral, it becomes a great virtue. Giving the, he says,
"TSUN" here means,
BYIN PA TSUN  means on down to giving
French fries to a bird, on down to giving French fries to a bird or
even going to the toilet that we also thought as something neutral
becomes a high bodhisattva act. That's awesome. You know, that's awesome if we can have this
background motivation all the time, that I would like to, I would like
to, I
would like to as a parent save every living being. If you think like that, then
all the little stuff you do, brushing your teeth,
cleaning your house, it all becomes
high
karma. So everything you do become some kind of supercharged karma. You don't have any neutral actions
anymore, everything you do is super charged. That's very cool.
RDZOGS BYANG THOB PA'I RGYUR 'GYUR
And all of those actions, cleaning your house, brushing your teeth, going to the bathroom at
McDonald's, feeding the birds, they all become direct causes for Buddhahood. Okay, very cool.
Now,
BYANG SEMS BDAG NYID CHEN POS NI, MI DGE BA'ANG
BA'ANG 'DIS ZIN NAS DGE BAR BSGYUR NUS PA YIN,
Now this is a very controversial statement. I don't want you to hear it.
And then everybody's like, "Tell me."
BYANG CHUB, BYANG SEMS BDAG NYID CHEN POS. BDAG NYID CHEN POS, $50, Sanskrit.
BDAG NYID CHEN POS
Cancel. Mahatma. Okay, Mahatma.
This is the Tibetan from Mahatma and it means a great being. It means a great being.
Like Mahatma Gandhi.
BYANG SEMS means those bodhisattva, mahatmas.
I don't know. Let's think of something.
Yeah, okay, you go to McDonald's,
you want to give French fries to the birds as a bodhisattva activity
and
then you find out you don't have any money or credit card.
And you go outside and there's a guy sitting next to your eating French fries.
He looks away and you swipe a French fry
and you give it to the birds.
Under special circumstances,
if your motivation is high enough,
that
stealing a French fry
becomes a good karma.
Because of the motivation. And that's an extremely dangerous idea.
Okay. I was trying to think of some picture that I could show you that
would demonstrate how dangerous this idea is, so I got this picture of a Fugu fish
in Japan. A Fugu fish is also called a Blowfish and
there are parts of inside this fish that are highly, highly poisonous.
They are more poisonous than cyanide.
So, I don't know there's this, I don't know Japanese
cool people and I spent time working in Japan, there's this thing of,
courage thing, bravery thing.
They say, "Give me a,"  they to a restaurant to say, "Give me a F,ugu fish." And
the guys like, "But you know, if you eat the wrong piece you will die here now
with the fish in your mouth, you will die that fast,"
And I looked it up, 50 people die in Japan every year from Fugu fish.
They're like, "I'm going to try."
It's supposed to be, it's super delicious because it's so dangerous.
To cook it legally
you have to have three years of training.
You have to have a license and you have to have three years of training to legally serve it in a restaurant, to cook it.
Most of people who die by one and take it home and trying to do themselves.
So, you know what I'm talking about, right?
You got what I'm talking about, right?
To steal the French fry and
give it to the birds
takes a very skilled, highly trained
bodhisattva cook. If you and me try it we will just end up on the floor dead
with Fugu fish in our mouth.
You know and there's, if there's a,
there's a joke, that no matter how many times you tell a student something's dangerous, someone's going to try it anyway.
So, please don't, okay.
He's just trying to make a point that
things that are normally not nice...
These high, high bodhi, BDAG NYID CHEN POS  means not just a normal bodhisattva,
but a very high bodhisattva.
It's possible they could steal a French fry and,
what do you call it? Turn it over into an incredible good deed. But it's extremely rare.
Like eating Fugu fish. Okay. So don't be a fool, a Fugu fool. All right?.
‘DI MED NA NI, STONG NYID RTOGS PA'I
SHES RAB RKYEN DANG PHRAD NA,
THEG PA GSUM GA'I BYANG CHUB KYI
RGYUR 'GRO BAS MA LTA BU YIN LA,
BYANG SEMS NI BLA MED BYANG
CHUB KHO NA'I RGYUR 'GYUR BAS
PHA DANG 'DRA BA YIN NO,
,DES NA SNGA MA LA YUM YANG ZER,
'DIS ZIN NAS DGE BAR BSGYUR NUS PA YIN,
‘DI MED NA NI,
STONG NYID RTOGS PA'I SHES RAB RKYEN DANG
Okay.
In general,
seeing emptiness directly. Okay,
STONG NYID RTOGS PA'I SHES RAB here.
If you
can see emptiness directly,
THEG PA GSUM GA'I BYANG CHUB KYI RGYUR 'GRO
So this BYANG CHUB here
does not mean BYANG CHUB SEMS PA
It does not mean, mean Bodhisattva.
It means Buddhahood, but it doesn't mean Buddhahood.
It means enlightenment of the three kinds,
of the three vehicles, of the three tracks.
There are two lower tracks.
If you get to the end of them because you saw emptiness directly without bodhichitta,
then those do create nirvana, but it's
called lower nirvana. And we already talked
about how we don't want to go there. Okay?
But seeing emptiness directly
has that power
even for a person who doesn't have a
high motivation. So even for a person who
does not have a high motivation,
seeing emptiness directly can give birth inside of them to nirvana and therefore is called MA.
It's called the Mother, YUM like,
YAB YUM okay? It's called the Mother.
So here it's MA, MA LTA BU YIN.
I'd like to go to the next
picture
which I negotiated with
very, with great difficulty,
from a family in
in Sedona. Okay, and
here you see Erin Schaad,
Mrs. Nick Lashaw, you see Nick Lashaw and you see their baby Amelie. Okay.
So just imagine
Amelie
being a Buddha, which is not
difficult looking at her face,
The, the Mother of the Buddha's, the Erin of
all Buddha's is the direct perception
of emptiness. So we can say
that seeing emptiness directly is the
Mother of the Buddha,like Erin for Amalie, okay?
BYANG SEMS NI BLA MED BYANG
CHUB KHO NA'I RGYUR 'GYUR BAS
PHA DANG 'DRA BA
But bodhichitta
only has one result. You can't go on the three tracks
after having that experience. Once
you've had that experience, the two lower
tracks are canceled. You are restricted to
the highest track. And the highest track,
the Bodhisattva track always ends in total Buddhahood. Complete Buddhahood.
BLA MED means the
highest, totally highest. Okay Incomparable. Nothing higher.
So KHO NA'I RGYUR 'GYUR BAS
So really it's like a father. If we go back to the photo,
Nick represents the
bodhichitta. Nick represents bodhichitta.
And the mom, there's something here,
I mean you guys got to think about it in your study groups maybe. There's some kind of statement here,
I don't know exactly what it is.
The emptiness
realization could go three ways.
You could become a complete Buddha or you could just reach nirvana. So therefore it's like a mother.
But the
bodhichitta can only go to full enlightenment. Therefore. It's like a father.
So maybe it's some statement about what
a mother is and what a father is,I don't know.
You guys can debate it in your discussion groups.
He's making some kind of statement like that.
'GYUR BAS PHA DANG 'DRA BA YIN NO,
,DES NA SNGA MA LA YUM YANG ZER,
And by the way, he makes an
aside, this is an aside.
He's making a side statement. He says that, "By the way
that's why we call the Perfection of Wisdom
YUM as in YAB YUM."
YUM means Holy Mother or something like that.
That's why we call the
Perfection of Wisdom, Holy Mother.
I looked up what YUM is in Sanskrit and it took me awhile.
Oftentimes, it's simply PRAJNAPARAMITA.
The Perfection of Wisdom,
but sometimes it's called Mata.
Which means mother.
Then Indian people call their mom's Mataji.
So YUM in Tibetan,
referring to the direct perception
emptiness and the literature that helps you get there,
the Mother sutras or the Mother,
The Great Mother.
Alright,
and together they're called mata, pita or
pita, oh no,
sorry. Mata, pita or
amba. Sometimes AMBA
for the mom or sometimes
PITARMATAR, which means father and mother.
Alright, last part here.
MDOR NA SANGS RGYAS KYI GO
'PHANG ZHIG 292B DON DU MI
GNYER NA MA GTOGS,
This is an interesting statement.
THAMS CAD KYIS BYANG CHUB KYI
SEMS LA THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL DU BYA
Okay.
There's a word here in the second
line called THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL
THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL,
at the end of the second line here.
Yeah, and MTHIL means the palm of
your hand. This is ..MTHIL. This is
...MTHIL, okay. The palm of your foot, this sole of your foot, okay.
And
...MTHIL means...
You know, so I got a I got a piece of gum here and
if you hold out your hand and you put it in
the middle of your hand, okay, that's called
...MTHIL. And it means
what's your one most important Buddhist practice?
It's called What's in the Palm of your Hand. It's kind of funny.
By the way, the name of the book is not
Liberation in the Palm of Your Hand.
The name of the book is A Gift of Liberation Shoved into Your Open Hands.
Thank you. I wasn't expecting that.
But this palm, it means look,
what's the one practice
you should always have at hand, in your hands?
What's your one...
THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL means
What is your private number one practice?
What is your number one
dharma theme for your whole life?
You know, which have you selected?
Is it Vajra Yogini practice or is it death meditation or is it seeing emptiness directly?
What's the one thing you want to be buried with?
What's the one thing you want in your hand?
SANGS RGYAS KYI GO 'PHANG
ZHIG DON DU MI GNYER NA MA
Now, first he excludes a certain group
of people. First he excludes a
certain group of people.
He says, "Look,
I'm not talking about people
who don't want to become a Buddha.
Forget those people." It's really funny. I don't know why he said that, you know, he says, "Look what I'm about to say,
it's just meant for you guys who want to become a Buddha.  So if you don't want to become a Buddha
then don't listen to this next part."
He says, "If you're not interested in becoming Buddha, then you don't have to listen to this part.
But, if you are interested in being a Buddha
then there's only one, you
know,
practice you should devote your whole life to.
The one practice you keep in the palm hand."
And that's you've got to have this experience
where you meet
every single being, one-by-one and commit to,
you commit to help them
overcome all pain. You make that personal connection
and commitment to every single living being.
Bugs, fish, birds,
Martians,
people living on the other side
of the universe, all of them,
in a single meditation.
Let's make that the
one thing you're going to work on for the rest of your life. Let this be your heart practice.
All right, MTHIL DU BYA , THEG GSUM GYI YON TAN SOGS LEGS PA CI YOD THAMS CAD PHAR DED NA
This PHAR DED NA, okay.
Very, very unusual word.
You won't see it very often.
DED means to chase an animal while you're hunting it
Okay.
It's got a weird, it's a weird word.
Like you're hunting a rabbit and
you keep running after the rabbit.
That's called DED.
And PHAR DED as an idiom in Tibetan and
it means boils down to.
If you chase, chase, chase, chase, chase,
it all comes down to this. What? He says, "Look,
all of Buddhism, the whole Buddhist
practice, three hundred thousand John Brady books.
All, all Buddhist practice,
ultimately PHAR DED NA, it boils down to
trying to get this experience.
Trying to have this experience with every living being.
All Buddhist practice,
thousands and thousands of books.
Thousands of hours of meditation, it all boils down to
can you trigger this experience?
Can you have this experience yourself?
Very cool.
All right. See you in the next episode. Thank you.